[music]
>> Really what he was designing for and
what kind of singled him out was this
idea of designing for a kind of
independent woman.
>> It's fashion that [music] is looking to
separates, to clothing that is made of a
wide range of materials, not just the
usual things that you [music] would
expect from couture.
>> It was focused on cuts, on superb
fabrics, on clothes that weren't fussy.
His clothes stood for a certain kind of
streamlined elegance.
>> I think that's what we forget now when
we look back at Givenchy because it is
so perfect, it's so grown-up. [music]
It was seen as youthful.
>> Making clothes that in effect kind of
heralded the launch of designer
ready-to-wear in the 1960s. [music]
Really what he offered to couture
clients specifically was kind of a a
gentle passage into that new era.
>> [music]
>> Hubert de Givenchy was born to an
aristocratic [music] family in Was,
France on February 21st, 1927.
>> Hubert de Givenchy was born as a member
of the French aristocracy. His father
died when he was quite young and he was
raised um around his mother and his
maternal grandmother.
>> As with so many aristocrats of the time,
there was a real sort of appreciation
for luxury,
um for textiles as part of [music] that
and also a background within his family
of textile mills.
>> The family had a textile
company which must have been extremely
helpful
when wanting to be a designer. So he
developed [music]
a sort of rather refined taste and and
knowledge of fabrics early on.
>> At age 10, Hubert visited the 1937
World's Fair in Paris and was instantly
inspired. This event, in conjunction
with his love of textiles, played a
large part in a young Givenchy promptly
deciding [music] that his future lay
somewhere in fashion design.
>> [music]
>> It exposed him as kind of a
creatively influenced youngster to
textiles from all around the world. And
really that was the idea of being
exposed to something very different to
the high French couture of that time.
>> [music]
>> That connection between commerce and and
making and manufacturing and the role of
textiles within design was really
fundamental [music] from the start for
him.
>> He saw fabrics from all over the world.
This made him want to explore more. It
made him want to see more of the world.
And I think he sniffed freedom from the
mother and
the grandmother. And Paris, [music] here
he came.
>> When he was 17, he went to the École des
Beaux-Arts
to pursue a career in fashion design.
That was his aim from his earliest
upbringing.
>> When you think what was happening in
Paris at that time, with the Nazi
occupation, that people were still going
to college and learning the art of of
couture is is extraordinary.
And then he he his first apprenticeship
was with Jacques Fath.
>> He began an apprenticeship with the
designer Jacques Fath, who his family
members knew personally. The next 7
years saw him continuing to learn the
art of the couturier from Robert Piguet
and doing designs for Lucien Lelong.
>> He worked for Lucien Lelong, so someone
who was really important within the
Chambre Syndicale. And someone who was
also really canny in understanding the
importance of America and understanding
the importance of consolidating an idea
of what your fashion house stands for.
>> When he worked at Lucien Lelong, he
actually worked alongside Christian Dior
and Pierre Balmain who were both
designing at the same time, as well as
Marc Bohan.
He would have been exposed to what were
some of the largest and best couture
ateliers in in Paris.
>> The world still looks to Paris, despite
its temporary eclipse during the war, as
the historic source of creative fashion,
a position it has maintained for
centuries.
>> [music]
>> In the subsequent years, he collaborated
with Elsa Schiaparelli. It's very
interesting that he worked with
Schiaparelli. Lots of people don't know
that because her style is very, very
flamboyant, theatrical, a lot of
surrealism,
Dadaism in her in her work. So, maybe he
ran in the opposite direction from from
what Elsa [music]
had taught him.
>> He made a lot of separates for her
boutique, and that's something that he
then comes on to be really very well
known [music] for.
>> Givenchy made a lasting impression on
the Parisian fashion scene. Thanks to
his remarkably tall frame and uniquely
elegant designs based on powerful
femininity, he was quite unforgettable.
In 1952, [music]
after being dismissed by Elsa
Schiaparelli, his own design house, the
revolutionary La Maison Givenchy, was
born.
>> Christian Dior was 42
by the time he presented his first
couture collection. It was really
revolutionary to see someone so young
founding a a couture house.
>> His first collection got rave reviews.
So, there was never any problem of
acceptance there.
>> [music]
>> L'Album de Figaro wrote a feature
stating that in one night Hubert de
Givenchy became one of fashion's [music]
most famous children with his first
collection.
>> They were raving about his young
clothes. I think that's what we forget
now when we look back at old Givenchy
because it is so perfect, it's so
grown-up. But it was seen as youthful.
>> He was a youthful couturier and he was
creating youthful clothes. It was almost
a precursor to the sort of couture we
see in the '60s with with Pierre Cardin
and Andre Courreges where there's very
much this focus [music] on on youth, on
a certain dynamism. And really
Givenchy's early designs had that.
>> [music]
>> His first notably exceptional sartorial
pieces were skirts and tailored blouses
made [music] from raw cotton.
>> There was a movement amongst the
bourgeoisie in the '50s for these rather
[music] sort of understated, quite
simple, almost peasant clothes. [music]
Of course, they were very, very refined.
So, they would be silks that looked like
linens. So, he made this collection from
cottons and it and it went down a storm.
>> He's really interested in quite mundane
fabrics like cotton, denim, leather,
fabrics that [music] perhaps wouldn't be
so immediately associated with couture,
but he's able to use them in such a way
that they become a sort of refined and
exquisite element within a design.
>> Givenchy designed separates which was
seen as something revolutionary for a
couturier to to propose a skirt and
blouse to women rather than a complete
look was really seen as as something
quite extraordinary.
>> They seem very fresh and new and very
practical as well.
>> Using these fabrics in a very, very
feminine [music] way, he's taking a
traditionally male fabric and using it
in a very feminine light. So, there's a
sort of
youthfulness and kind of almost
dewyness, I think, to his designs that
they're really, really fresh.
>> [music]
>> Named after his muse and model of the
day, Bettina Graziani, Givenchy created
the Bettina blouse.
>> It was cotton. It had a sort of wide
[music] open neck and it featured
English embroidery on it.
>> This Bettina blouse, which was kind of a
ruffled and flounced number, was made
out of cotton pique, which wasn't the
sort of fabric that people were used to
couturiers [music] using.
>> I think that's really quintessentially
Givenchy that it adds quite sharp
tailoring and knowledge of how tailoring
pulls into the body, but then very sort
of frivolous-seeming feminine elements
which are then [music] balanced with the
more masculine elements of the of the
shirt front and the fabric.
>> [music]
[singing]
>> In 1953, Givenchy met Audrey Hepburn. It
was to be the start of a lifelong
relationship and through the global
reach of Hollywood, it allowed
Givenchy's designs to be showcased
around the world.
>> I think it's a really interesting story
how he meets Audrey Hepburn that she is
actually it's via a a Schiaparelli
contact that she um is brought to his
house and it's when he she is looking
for um costumes for Sabrina.
>> Well, hello. How are you?
>> When Audrey Hepburn first met Hubert de
Givenchy, he was incredibly disappointed
because he actually thought it was going
to be Katharine Hepburn that he was
going to be dressing.
Um and then [music] this kind of little
wife turned up.
>> But I think when she arrived in a little
sort of shirt just knotted at the waist
and
I think little capri pants and ballet
[music]
uh shoes. I mean, he could just see that
this was an actress who had
absolute innate [music] style.
>> You look lovely, Sabrina.
>> He sort of describes her as coming in
and having quite a sort of eclectic
eccentric [music]
style, but incredibly charming within
that and and
>> [music]
>> I think it's it's that kind of meeting
of someone in Audrey Hepburn's case who
is fascinated by clothing, but had not
[music] yet found her her oeuvre, if you
like. She hadn't quite found the design
that spoke of her body, that spoke of
her idea of femininity.
>> Kiss me, David.
>> I'd love to, Sabrina.
>> He dressed her for Sabrina to great
acclaim and also found that she had a
genuine love for fashion. She was born
in Belgium, so they had kind of an
affinity in in terms of that European
upbringing.
>> [music]
>> Givenchy's big breakthrough was
Breakfast at Tiffany's. [music]
And arguably that's his most famous
contribution and his most famous [music]
dresses the one that Hepburn wears when
she's um sort of having an early
breakfast outside the Tiffany shop in
New York.
>> It's interesting that he his dress was
used in Breakfast at Tiffany's because
obviously Holly Golightly was seen as
this kind of free-spirited kind of
modern woman um rather than the sort of
corseted and corseted women that were
represented by Christian Dior's new
look.
>> Even people who've never seen the film
know the poster. I mean, it's one of the
most famous artifacts of the 20th
century, the poster of Audrey Hepburn
with the cigarette holder and the little
black [music] dress. And that little
black dress still looks pretty modern
today.
>> The dress is a column dress. It's more
sophisticated. It's a more grown-up idea
of eveningwear.
>> After that, she had it written into her
contract that I am dressed by Hubert and
it's rather a smart [music] thing to
have done.
>> The fact that he continually dressed her
throughout all of her films, they stand
as kind of archetypes for what people
understood as Givenchy's style, which
was a style that was very spare, that
was focused on cuts, on superb fabrics,
on clothes that weren't fussy. I think
that's really what he his clothes stood
for, a certain kind of streamlined
elegance.
>> He did eight films with Audrey all
together right up till 1979, I think.
So, that was an incredibly fruitful
meeting that he had that day with Audrey
and and it really influenced the way he
designed. She just looks so joyful and
so
just filled with happiness when she put
on his clothes and I think that's what
you see radiating from her when she
wears her designs and what makes them so
appealing and really brings them to life
and really unites the two of them.
>> She was the dream muse for any designer
but particularly
brought out the best in in Hubert and he
was a very charming man as well
and I I think Chanel could have dressed
Audrey Hepburn but I think the
relationship might not have been as
enduring. I think it would have been
much more prickly.
>> [music]
>> At the age of 25, Hubert de Givenchy was
the youngest designer in the developing
Parisian fashion scene. He had become
very famous in a short space of time.
Givenchy's credibility expanded when he
met Cristóbal Balenciaga. That same
year, one of Givenchy's designs was on
the cover of Life magazine.
>> What happened really is that Balenciaga
became a mentor for Givenchy.
>> The way that Balenciaga would remove
restrictions from clothes, you know, he
didn't want to upholster women the way
that that Dior has been accused of
doing. I think really that translated
into Hubert de Givenchy's designs but
with less grandeur, with less drama,
something that was more realistic,
something that was more everyday almost.
>> And so what you see is more classical
line to a line [music] that's more
architectural and more considered. And
you know, he even moves his couture
house so that he's opposite Balenciaga.
So, there's sort of physical proximity
as well as sort of intellectual and
[music] creative proximity between the
two of them.
>> Givenchy and Balenciaga collaborated in
1957 to create a new silhouette called
the sack, a loose dress lacking a
defined waistline.
>> Designs which become so famous like the
sack back dress, [music] which is an
interesting modernist rethinking of an
18th century style that puts
>> [music]
>> weight onto the back of a dress, so it
sort of flows down from the shoulders.
>> It was extremely elegant and [music]
very hard to do well.
>> And it was very very fresh because, you
know, we we'd had all this focus on the
[music] waist and the and the buffy big
skirts.
>> I can't really think of another example
where you have designers couturiers
>> [music]
>> working so closely together and being so
explicit about it and not being
kind of egotistical and saying trying to
claim it for themselves, [music] but
that that it's something that's come out
of talking together, working together
and a shared aesthetic.
>> Originally created exclusively [music]
for Audrey Hepburn, Givenchy released
his perfume L'Interdit in 1957. [music]
It was the first time the world had ever
seen the face of a celebrity on a
perfume.
>> There had been kind of Elsa Schiaparelli
Shocking, which was linked abstractly to
May West,
but L'Interdit was the first time that a
celebrity had openly endorsed a
couturier's perfume.
>> It was really significant in that it had
so much deeper resonance because of
their existing relationship.
>> He'd made it specially for her
originally, which is I think such a
[music] a lovely a lovely
>> And I mean, so often now when designers
launch perfumes, they've just gone to
Procter & Gamble and sort of taken
something off the shelf. The fact that
this man had developed this perfume for
one woman is really quite magical.
>> With somebody like Audrey Hepburn, when
she's tied so intrinsically to a house
like Givenchy,
it really takes that kind of celebrity
endorsement to another level.
>> As Givenchy's designs received huge
international success. America's first
lady, Jacqueline Kennedy, caused a stir
by wearing a Givenchy evening dress
during a visit to Paris in 1961.
>> It caused a bit of a fuss back in
America because first ladies were meant
to wear American designers.
And she got wrapped on the knuckles.
>> Givenchy, [music] with this Hollywood
connection, was kind of a French style
that Americans could relate to. It was a
French name that Americans could relate
to.
>> She did look very regal in it. And I
think [music]
that contributed to the whole
aristocratic clothes horse view of of
Jackie that
was incredibly seductive to many people,
but also
alienating to some.
>> Throughout the 1960s, fashion changed
and the ready-to-wear market boomed.
Givenchy retained much appeal,
particularly with women of the
aristocracy, such as Wallis [music]
Simpson, the Duchess of Windsor, and the
Princess Grace.
>> Givenchy had that kind of confidence of
aristocracy, that assurance of knowing
his position in society.
>> And I think what drew them to Givenchy
was that his clothing
was always very proper. That it was um
very beautifully designed and made. It
was flattering. It was wearable. It was
drawing attention to the woman for the
right reasons.
>> I think the interesting thing with
Wallis Windsor wearing Givenchy to the
the Duke of Windsor's funeral is really
to see that in the [music] continuum of
her style. She was said to be the most
elegant woman alive. And the fact that
she chose Givenchy for such a pivotal
moment is incredibly important. It's a
real stamp of what he stood for at that
point in in French fashion, which I
think was a stamp for tradition, but not
necessarily a stamp for staidness.
>> As mainstream consumer [music] needs
continued to move away from haute
couture and into ready to wear, fashion
houses across the world saw a sudden
change in demand.
>> There was one season, basically when
department stores just stopped buying
haute couture and started to buy
ready-to-wear. Why would you license
haute couture and have copies made at
your own expense when you could just buy
the designer ready-to-wear and it was
already made for you?
So, really it kind of it pricked the
bubble, it all collapsed. Yves Saint
Laurent said that couture [music] was
dead in 1971. The whole world sort of
changed. I think she she was probably
quite scared by that.
>> In 1973, [music]
his first men's ready-to-wear line was
established. Throughout the '70s and
'80s, the Givenchy brand expanded
worldwide into many different areas with
much [music] success. His Lincoln Mark V
car designed in the 1970s sold out
immediately.
>> Why do you sleep so still?
>> For a lot of the older couture clients,
as people like Dior died, as Balenciaga
closed his house, as [music] the the
houses that they'd always gone to, they
all flocked to Givenchy because they
knew that he would dress them in a
manner that wasn't controversial, that
wasn't aggressive, that wasn't going to
kind of shock their friends or husbands.
>> As the years progressed, Givenchy
continued to thrive in a ever-changing
world of fashion.
>> [music]
>> In 1983,
Vivienne Westwood showed her collection
in Paris and newspaper reporters said
that you had to miss Givenchy to see it,
but it was [music] worth it. And really
that kind of sets the pace for Givenchy,
who was continuing in a very quiet way,
but [music] certainly not reacting to
kind of the the new landscape of
fashion.
>> [music]
>> In 1988, Givenchy decided to sell his
fashion house to the LVMH group.
>> I think he was coming to the end of his
career. He was increasingly out of sync
with contemporary fashions
Um and it was a period when big
>> [music]
>> luxury brands like LVMH were looking to
buy older established couture houses and
reimagine them for the late [music] 20th
century.
>> In the 1980s and early 90s, LVMH was
building up a portfolio of brands um
and was really seen as somebody that was
resurrecting French [music] haute
couture.
>> I imagine that they made him an offer he
couldn't refuse and that he was getting
on a bit and he didn't have an obvious
heir.
>> I think it was the continuation of his
name. They were really seen as kind of
saviors of French fashion. I think what
Givenchy hoped to do by selling his
house to to LVMH was to secure its
future.
>> [music]
>> Givenchy continued to design for the
house until 1995 when he would present
his ultimate collection.
>> It then [music] went through quite a
sort of rapid succession of designers.
John Galliano was there prior to going
to Dior. McQueen was there quite
unhappily
>> [music]
>> for a brief spell. Julien Macdonald was
there for a brief spell.
>> The onus there was really on on
ready-to-wear and on making something
that had an impact at ready-to-wear
and an impact at haute couture. [music]
It wasn't so much about dressing people
anymore. It was about creating
these images that would sell Givenchy
perfume, that would sell Givenchy makeup
and would also sell accessories.
>> Then Riccardo [music] Tisci took over
and really what he has done is
rethink what Givenchy stands for
but [music] still very much focusing on
youth.
>> He's got great friendship with Kanye
West and [music] Kim Kardashian.
They have been at a lot of his shows.
They wear the clothes. Rihanna wears the
clothes. It's become very sexy.
>> There's a sense of sort of youthfulness
and [music] being inspired by street
culture subculture. So, it's a very
different kind of Givenchy, but staying
true to some of its [music] original
ideas.
>> It's a new way of looking at houses and
looking at existing fashion houses in
the 21st century. Is this idea of going
in,
taking the name and then doing whatever
you want underneath it. And I really
think that's why Givenchy is successful
now, it's because of Riccardo Tisci,
because of people reacting to his
aesthetic, [music]
rather than necessarily reacting to the
name Givenchy or the legacy of the
house.
>> [music]
>> The Givenchy brand continues to be a
world leader in the global fashion
industry. [music] Throughout his career,
Hubert de Givenchy was nominated for an
Academy Award for Funny Face, featured
on the international best-dressed
[music] list, and received a Lifetime
Achievement Award. There have been
exhibitions of his work around the
world, and he has [music] been an
inspiration to many designers.
>> In the 60 years since Hubert [music] de
Givenchy set up his his house,
his work has been in countless
exhibitions. People see it all the time
without necessarily knowing that they're
looking at Givenchy.
>> I think really what Hubert de Givenchy
will be remembered for
is actually a very brief, but very
tumultuous period in French haute
couture. [music]
It's that move from the '50s into the
'60s. It's that move from people wanting
[music] to dress like their mothers into
mothers wanting to dress like their
daughters.
>> I think he's someone who had a very
[music] successful house, a very
successful career. I think he was very
good at disseminating
>> [music]
>> and publicizing his look through
collaboration with Hepburn and other
stars.
>> I think his clothes are [music]
timeless, and I think the femininity and
the elegance
>> [music]
>> that he
espoused
and did so beautifully. Even now, if you
ask most women how they [music] want to
dress, it isn't even necessarily
fashionably, they just want to look
elegant. They would love that, wouldn't
we all? And I think that's what that's
what Schiaparelli did for women.
>> [music]
[music]